他连狩猎都要带着留声机
He even took the Gramophone on safari.
三把来福枪...
Three rifles...
一个月的补给品 还有莫扎特
supplies for a month and Mozart.
我们的友谊从一份礼物开始
He began our friendship with a gift.
后来...
And later...
在去察沃之前...
not long before Tsavo...
他送我另外一份礼物
he gave me another.
一样奇妙的礼物
An incredible gift.
从上帝的眼中看这个世界
A glimpse of the world through God's eye.
我告诉自己...
And I thought...
"我明白了
"Yes, I see.
这一切都是神的旨意"
This is the way it was intended."
我写了其他的人...
I've written about all the others...
不是因为不够爱他们...
not because I loved them less...
是因为他们的故事比较好写
but because they were clearer, easier.
他一直在我的记忆中
He was waiting for me there.
但是我故事说的太快了 他最讨厌这样
But I've gone ahead of my story. He'd have hated that.
丹尼斯喜欢人家从头说起
Denys loved to hear a story told well.
你知道...
You see...
我在非洲有座农场...
I had a farm in Africa...
在尼刚山脚下
at the foot of the Ngong Hills.
但故事不是从那里开始
But it began before that.
真正开始是在丹麦
It really began in Denmark.
我认识一对兄弟
And there I knew two brothers.
一个是我的情人 一个是我的朋友
One was my lover, and one was my friend.
- 冷天不该喝香槟的  - 冷天才该喝香槟
- It's too cold for champagne.  - It's too cold for anything but.
你说你会来克莱本堡的
You said you'd be at Klampenborg.
我以为我会去 结果没有
I thought I'd come, but then I didn't.
好玩吗?
Was it fun?
恬妮?
Tanne?
恬妮 别这样
Tanne, come on.
你又不爱他
It's not as though you loved him.
你只是想当男爵夫人 仅此而已
You'd like to be a baroness, that's all.
- 他骗我  - 当然
- He lied to me.  - Of course.
不然你会和他上床吗?
Would you be in bed with him otherwise?
我哥哥是迟钝 但是不笨
My brother's only dull, but not stupid.
假装它是汉斯
Pretend it's Hans.
- 你打算去哪?  - 哪都行
- Where would you go?  - Anywhere.
美国 锡兰 甚至澳大利亚都行
America. Ceylon. I would even go to Australia.
也许不去澳大利亚 反正我要离开这里
Well, perhaps not Australia. But I've got to be away from here.
我会尽力帮你
I'll give you all I've got.
应该可以帮你达到目的 天哪 有钱真好
That should get you into town. God, it was fun with money.
- 你可以娶我  - 我必须娶处女
- You could marry me.  - I have to marry a virgin.
我受不了批评
I can't stand criticism.
我的意思是 为了钱
For the money, I mean.
也许
Probably.
波尔 听我说 我没有人生目标
Bror, listen to me. I've got no life at all.
也没有一技之长
They wouldn't teach me anything useful.
现在又嫁不出去 你知道我的下场
Now I've failed to marry. You know the punishment for that.
"嫁不出去的老小姐"
"Miss Dinesen's at home."
而你的钱已经花光了 也不再引诱女佣
You've gone through all your money. You're off seducing the servant girls.
我们是一对 你和我
We're a pair, you and I.
我是说 至少我们是朋友
I mean, at least we're friends.
我们应该会成功 就算不成...
We might be all right. And if we weren't...
至少我们试过了
at least we'd have been somewhere.
你不觉得太异想天开了吗?
You don't think you're being too romantic?
恬妮
Tanne
你是认真的吗?
Am I supposed to think you're serious?
我在非洲有座农场
I had a farm in Africa.
"1913年 东非肯尼亚" 我在非洲有座农场...
I had a farm in Africa...
在尼刚山脚下
at the foot of Ngong Hills.
我在非洲有座农场
I had a farm in Africa.
片名: 走出非洲
- 早安  - 你有困难吗?
- Good morning.  - Have you had trouble?
偶尔 你有吗?
Now and then. Have you?
没有 我要去奈洛比
No. I'm travelling to Nairobi.
那你没搭错车
Well, you caught the right train.
走开! 嘘! 嘘!
Get away! Shoo! Shoo!
那箱是我的水晶 还有瓷器
That's all my crystal. My Limoges.
他们不知道是瓷器
They didn't know it was Limoges.
那你打算留下来咯?
So you plan to stay, then?
我是来和毕斯男爵结婚的 你认识他吗?
I've come out to marry Baron Blixen. Do you know him?
- 波尔? 认识  - 我们打算经营农场
- Bror? Yes.  - We plan to start a dairy.
你很有名吗? 他们为了你停车
Are you quite famous? They stopped the train for you.
这是一种礼貌
It's rude not to here.
农场 叫他们订牛奶不嫌太快了?
A dairy. Isn't it a bit soon for milk at the door?
- 你不上车吗?  - 不 我还要继续
- Aren't you boarding?  - No, I'm going on.
继续? 去哪?
On? To where?
告诉柯尔象牙的事 波尔知道他是谁
Mention the ivory to Berkeley Cole. Bror knows him.
我是毕斯男爵夫人!
I'm Baroness Blixen!
还不是
Not yet.
费奇哈顿 或者丹尼斯!
Finch Hatton, Denys!
夫人 我是法拉
Msabu, I am Farah Aden.
我们可以走了
We can go now.
- 毕斯男爵呢?  - 他在姆泰加
- Where is Baron Blixen?  - He's at Muthaiga.
请跟我来
Please, come.
姆泰加在哪?
Where is Muthaiga?
那是英国人喝酒的俱乐部
Muthaiga is a club where British go for drinking.
请
Please.
还有 木箱里装的是瓷器和水晶
Listen. On the train are my crates with china and crystal.
- 你知道瓷器吧?  - 知道 夫人
- Do you know china?  - Yes, msabu.
瓷器 一摔就破
China, it can break.
等我
Stay.
对不起 我在找毕斯男爵
Excuse me. I'm looking for Baron Blixen.
拉吉夫
Rajiv.
- 不知道你...  - 这里不欢迎女士
- Yes. I wondered if you might...  - Memsahibs must not be here.
- 我只是在找...  - 这里不欢迎女士
- I'm simply looking...  - Memsahibs must not be here.
你跑哪去了?
Where have you been?
- 你到底跑哪去了?  - 安排事情
- Where have you been?  - Arranging things.
旅途愉快吗? 待会儿再告诉我
How was the trip? You can tell me later.
- 你要换衣服吗?  - 我的行李还在火车上
- Would you like to change?  - My luggage is still on the train.
D号房 在楼上 我还没买戒指
Room "D," head of the stairs. I haven't done anything about a ring.
- 你介意吗?  - 你不认为我会来?
- Do you care?  - Did you think I wouldn't come?
我不认为你会想花这笔钱 你会喜欢这里
I didn't think you'd want to spend the money. You will love it here.
服务非常周到 要不要喝一杯?
Servants are wonderful. Shall we get a drink?
婚礼还有一个小时就开始
We've got almost one hour before the wedding.
一个小时?
One hour?
- 好看吗?  - 我在想你会选什么颜色
- Is it all right?  - I wondered what colour you'd choose.
是象牙色 对了
It's ivory. Oh, my God.
- 那个男人的象牙在我这里  - 谁的象牙?
- I've got this man's ivory.  - Whose ivory?
我是莎拉 贝福夫人 要不要我陪你?
I'm Sarah, Lady Belfield. Shall I stand up for you?
- 谢谢  - 长还是短?
- Thank you.  - Short or long?
长 让我有时间习惯
Long, please. Give me time to adjust to it.
大家安静
Settle down, all.
藉由皇帝陛下赋与我的权利...
By the authority of His Majesty's government vested in me...
我宣布瑞典公民...
I declare that the Baron Bror Von Blixen...
波尔毕斯男爵和...
citizen of Sweden, and...
- 你叫什么名字?  - 该死 亨利 我告诉过你的
- What's your name, my dear?  - Damn it, Henry, I told you her name.
凯伦丹森
Karen Christentze Dinesen.
丹麦国王的臣民...
Karen Christentze Dinesen...
凯伦丹森...
a female subject of the King of Denmark...
现在正式结为夫妻
are henceforth united man and wife.
愿主保佑这对夫妻 愿主保佑吾皇
God save this company. God save the king.
谢谢你
Thank you for this.
听说夏特华的事了吗? 我回答 没有
Did you hear about Shuttleworth? No, I said.
他说 "他和一只狒狒住在树上"
"He's living up country," he says "in a tree with a baboon."
我问他 "公的还是母的?"
"Male or female?" I said to him.
他回答 "当然是母的"
"Female, of course." he says.
"这还需要问嘛!"
"There's nothing queer about old Shuttleworth."
莎拉 你的糊涂丈夫在哪?
Sarah, where's your muddle-headed husband?
总督在喝甜酒 希望能躲开你
The governor's at the punch bowl hoping to avoid you.
你是来看新娘子 还是来喝威士忌的?
Would you like to meet the bride, or did you just come for the whisky?
当然不是来找朋友的
Not for the company, God knows.
我来介绍一下 这位是毕斯男爵夫人
Lord Delamere, may I present Baroness Blixen?
毕斯男爵夫人 这位是狄米领主
Baroness Blixen, Lord Delamere, such as he is.
男爵夫人 你是瑞典人?
Baroness. A Swede, are you?
不是 是丹麦人
No. Danish, actually.
德国旁边的那个小国家
The little country next to Germany.
要是开战 丹麦会支持谁?
If it comes to war, where will Denmark stand?
希望会选择中立 我们一向如此
On its own, I hope. We do have that history.
我们怎么称呼你? 男爵夫人太见外了
Is there something we can call you that gets around this "baroness"?
他们怎么称呼你?
What do they call you?
不介意的话 叫我狄米
"D," if I'm lucky.
我叫菲莉丝 我喜欢你的洋装
My stupid name's Felicity, but I do like your dress.
哦 谢谢
Oh, thank you.
可是 那不太像帽子
That's not much of a hat, though.
这只是为了好看
It's meant to be stunning.
这边的太阳会晒死人
We die of sunstroke here.
至少我不会被蚊子咬到
At least I'm safe from the mosquitos.
好大一只
The big ones.
- 天哪  - 你紧张吗?
- Good Lord.  - You nervous?
我应该吗?
Should I be?
你知道
You know.
新婚之夜那些的
Wedding night and all that.
结果他们两个光着身子 附近连棵灌木都没有
So they're both naked and not a shrub in sight.
凯伦 见过维琪葛笙吗?
Karen, have you met Vicky Gresham?
男爵夫人 我该行礼 但是我喝醉了
Hello, Baroness. I'd curtsy, but I'm drunk.
- 可以谈谈吗?  - 失陪一下
- May I see you, please?  - Excuse me.
你想认识朋友的话 最好在这里
If you want any friends, I'd make them here.
- 不然就没机会了  - 我要看我的房子
- There's no one else.  - I want to see my house.
那你最好换衣服
You may want to change.
要坐两个小时的车
It's a two-hour ride.
不好意思
Excuse me.
我的天 这些人真会喝
My God, these people drink.
对不起 我只是...
I'm sorry. I was just...
- 我想...  - 没关系
- I'm afraid...  - No, it's all right.
我想你发现我在偷看了
I'm afraid you've caught me snooping.
这不是我的房间 是丹尼斯的 他不会介意
It's not my room. It's Denys's. And Denys won't mind.
他个性就是那样
That's the thing about Denys.
你是柯尔?
Are you Cole?
巴克利柯尔
Berkeley Cole.
象牙是我带来的
I brought the ivory with me on the train.
呃 谢谢你
Well, thank you.
- 吃了奎宁没?  - 吃了
- You taking your quinine?  - Oh, yes.
他的书真多
He has got lovely books.
- 他借人吗?  - 我们有一个朋友...
- Does he lend them?  - We had a friend...
叫贺普华 向丹尼斯借了一本书没还
Hopworth, he'd got a book from Denys and didn't return it.
丹尼斯气坏了 我对他说...
Denys was furious. I said to Denys...
"你不会为了一本书失去一个朋友"
"You wouldn't lose a friend for the sake of a book."
"不会" 他说 "但是他已经气坏了"
He said, "No, but he has, hasn't he?"
- 你是从伦敦过来的?  - 不是 是从罗马
- Did you come out through London?  - No, from Rome, actually.
我以为你会有报纸
I thought you might have a newspaper.
没有 抱歉
No. Sorry.
反正也没什么好看
Oh, nothing in them anyway.
我以前常带一个朋友 去参加牛津的舞会
I had a friend who I used to take to the dances at Oxford.
舞会在六月 在河边举行
They were in June by the river.
她总是穿一件丝洋装
She always wore a new silk dress.
我觉得你们擦的香水一样
I think you're wearing her perfume.
不是
No.
味道很香 但是不一样
It's very nice, but it's not the same.
我们可以走了
We can go now.
这是贝纳
This is Belknap.
- 他管农场  - 晚安 夫人
- He runs the farm.  - Good evening, ma'am.
这是你的厨师 叫伊萨
This is your cook. Name's Esa.
这是裘马 佣人
And this is Juma. Houseboy.
来 看看你的家
Come. See your house.
你要是离开我 我就嫁给巴克利柯尔
When you leave me, I'm going to marry Berkeley Cole.
- 一个生意人  - 那是他的职业?
- A man in trade.  - Is that what he does?
他和索马里族很要好
He's thick with the Somalis.
他的土地上有一群人 认为他是王子
There's a crowd of them on his land who think he's a prince.
费奇哈顿的象牙都交给他卖
He sells Finch Hatton's ivory.
贝纳看起来人不错
Belknap is a cheery sort.
他自己有一块地 上面种满了亚麻
Had a place of his own. Went belly up trying to grow flax.
- 他懂牲口吗?  - 我没有买牲口
- Does he know cattle?  - I didn't buy cattle.
我们要改种咖啡
We're going to grow coffee instead.
原来不是这样计划的
That's not what we planned.
你在丹麦 我必须做决定
You were in Denmark. I had to decide.
之前说好的
We made a decision.
我们根本不懂咖啡
We don't know anything about coffee.
- 只要种下去就行了  - 我们说好开农场的 我妈...
- You plant it, it grows.  - We said a dairy. My mother...
只要赚钱 你妈才不管是牛还是咖啡
Your mother doesn't care if it's cows or coffee as long as it pays.
你必须整天守着牛群
You have to be with a herd or things go wrong.
我可不是来非洲看牛的
I didn't come to Africa to sit with silly cows.
只要告诉她 我们改变主意就好了
Just tell her we changed our minds.
下次你改变主意...
Next time you change your mind...
用你自己的钱
you do it with your money.
你用钱买的是头衔 男爵夫人 他们不会相信我的
They bought you a title, Baronessa. They didn't buy me.
倒酒 给我爱人的兄弟
Fetch some wine for my lover's brother.
我认为你累了
I think you're tired.
小心点
Be careful.
我有没有告诉你汉斯来道别?
Did I tell you Hans came to say goodbye?
男爵在哪?
Where is Baron Blixen?
- 他去打猎了  - 有没有说什么时候回来?
- He's gone to hunt.  - Did he say when he'd return?
他说他会在下雨前回来
He says he can come before the rain.
今天会下雨吗?
Is it going to rain today?
夫人 还要好多天才会下雨
It can be many days before the rain, msabu.
在俄亥俄 我们放稻草人来吓鸟
In Ohio we put up scarecrow to keep the birds away.
在这里 你希望 豹可以抑制狒狒的繁殖
Here, you hope there's enough leopard to keep down the baboon.
它们还会吃掉你的狗 非洲就是这样
They'll take your dog too. But that's Africa.
- 我们要种多少地?  - 一千英亩
- How much will we plant?  - A thousand acres.
- 要多久的时间?  - 那得问奇纳裘伊
- How long will that take?  - That depends on Kinanjui.
他是吉库犹人的酋长 你必须去找他帮忙
He's chief of the Kikuyu. Gotta deal with him to get your help.
- 什么时候可以收成?  - 这些是树苗
- When will be our first harvest?  - Well, these are seedlings.
可能要三或四年的时间
It'll be three, maybe four years.
- 四年?  - 如果全部结果的话
- Four years?  - If they bear at all.
没有人种过这么高的咖啡树
No one's ever tried coffee this high.
- 我们这四年怎么活?  - 我正在筹钱回家
- What will we live on for four years?  - I'm working to get home.
你要是没钱 希望你现在可以告诉我
If you haven't got it, be good if you could tell me right now.
我们只种五百亩
We will plant 500.
奇纳裘伊酋长 我听说你非常有智慧...
Chief Kinanjui, I've heard you're wise...
等一下
Not now, please.
我盼望我们能合作
And I look forward to our dealings.
你的族人 他们是好工人...
Your Kikuyu are good workers...
我希望诚实 公平的...
and I look forward to dealing with them...
和他们交易
honestly and fairly.
夫人 酋长听不懂英文
Msabu, this chief has no British.
- 告诉他我是男爵夫人  - 夫人 他知道
- Tell him I am Baroness Blixen.  - Chief knows that, msabu.
那就告诉他 我刚才说的话
Well, then tell him what I said.
他说什么?
What did he say?
他说吉库犹人知道该怎么做
He says this Kikuyu can do this work.
他还说...
What else did he...
你的腿伤非常严重
Your leg is very sick.
你必须过来擦药
You must come to the house for medicine.
- 他明白我说什么吗?  - 明白 夫人
- Does he understand me?  - Yes, msabu.
你要是不来 其他的男孩会笑你胆小
If you don't come, the other boys will say you are afraid.
我呢 只会认为你不聪明
I, myself, will think only that you are foolish.
这个男孩必须来我家接受治疗
This boy must come to my house for treatment.
一定要叫他来
See that he does.
奇纳裘伊还说了什么?
What else did Kinanjui say?
他说咖啡树不能长这么高
He says coffee must not grow this high.
别理他 夫人 他毕竟是个吉库犹人
Never mind, msabu. He's a chief, but he's a Kikuyu.
如果你在这边拦一座水坝...
If you put a dam here to stop the water...
我就可以在旁边挖一个池塘
then I can make a pond here.
- 你会不会...  - 这些水必须回到蒙巴萨
- Do you know how...  - This water must go home to Mombasa.
等我们挖完 这些水就可以回家
It can go home after we make a pond.
夫人 这些水住在蒙巴萨
Msabu, this water lives at Mombasa.
那 走吧
Come, then.
别跑
I wouldn't run.
你一跑会让它以为你是猎物
If you do, she'll think you're something good to eat.
你... 你有枪吗?
Have you... Do you have a gun?
它不喜欢你的味道
She won't like the smell of you.
开枪啊
Shoot it.
它吃过早饭了
She's had breakfast.
别...
Don't...
- 快开枪  - 我们再等一下
- Please, shoot her.  - No, let's give her a moment.
哦 我的天 快开枪!
Oh, my God, shoot her!
你到底打算要让它靠多近?
Just how much closer did you expect to let her come?
再近一点
A bit.
它想看你会不会跑 那是它们的习惯 很像人
She wanted to see if you'd run. That's how they decide. A lot like people.
- 我差点变它的午餐!  - 那不是它的错 它是狮子
- She almost had me for lunch!  - It wasn't her fault. She's a lion.
- 那也不是我的错  - 你没有带枪吗?
- It wasn't mine.  - Doesn't that outfit come with a rifle?
在我的马鞍上
It's on my saddle.
最好随身带着 你的马靠不住
Better keep it with you. Your horse isn't much of a shot.
通知巴克利一声 他带了礼物给你
For Berkeley. He's brought you presents.
我们路过你家 所以来找你
We stopped by your house and them came looking for you.
天哪 你真细心
Good Lord, you're sweet.
其实是正好顺路 我们要去马加迪湖猎象
On the road, actually. We're off to Magadi to shoot some ivory.
至少 我现在有好酒 可以招待你们
Now, at least, I have something good to offer you.
你打算告诉巴克利 我刚才的糗事吗?
Did you intend to tell Berkeley what a fool I was?
- 她让一只狮子觉得很好奇  - 好奇?
- She had a lion a bit interested.  - A bit?
还没有好奇到要咬我
But not enough to bite.
只要你不连累别人...
It's all right to take a chance...
你是可以冒险的
as long as it's you who'll pay.
- 你不认为吗?  - 只有你会这么认为
- Wouldn't you say so?  - It's the sort of thing you'd say.
- 谢谢你  - 不客气 毕斯人呢?
- Thank you.  - Not at all. Where's Blix?
- 打猎去了  - 去很久了吗?
- Hunting.  - Has he been out long?
对
Yes.
那你会需要人聊天 该留下来吃晚饭吗 丹尼斯?
You'll need a good chat, then. Shall we stay to supper, Denys?
- 毕斯应该有夹克可以借我们  - 我可以有意见吗?
- Blix will have jackets we could use.  - Do I have anything to say in this?
- 不可以 但是你可以说完  - 我希望你们留下来
- Not really, but we'll hear you out.  - Then I would like you to stay.
很好 丹尼斯
Good. Denys.
我不知道 你会唱歌吗?
I don't know. Do you sing?
不会
Never.
你会说故事吗?
Can you tell a story?
那刚好是我最拿手的
I happen to be very good at stories.
我相信
I believe that.
你们不是要经营农场吗?
What's happened to the cows, the dairy?
我们改变主意 决定改种咖啡
We changed our minds. We'll grow coffee instead.
- 这么高 有点冒险  - 已经有人说过了
- A bit risky, this high.  - So I've been told.
- 你好像不担心  - 我认为他们只是没有试过
- Didn't seem to bother you.  - I think they just haven't tried.
每次我一不注意 这块地就开始变得荒凉
Every time I turn my back, it wants to go wild again.
那是迟早的问题
It will go wild.
- 你的手下...  - 卡努西亚
- Your man...  - Kanuthia.
- 他不是吉库犹人  - 不是
- He's not Kikuyu.  - No.
我该确定他有晚饭吃吗?
Shall I see that he's given supper?
你不用特别招呼他 谢谢 男爵夫人
Don't do anything for him, thank you, Baroness.
所有的索马里人都是这样 他们是唯一懂马的部落
It's true of all Somalis. They're the only tribe that knows horses.
他们不喝酒 不收利息 而且不追别人的太太
They don't drink, charge interest or chase other men's wives.
那得进城才办得到
Got to go to town for that.
你们知道所有的文学作品中...
Did you know that in all of literature...
没有一首诗是歌颂脚的
there's no poem celebrating the foot.
有赞美嘴唇 眼睛 手 脸...
There's lips, eyes, hands, face...
头发 胸部...
hair, breasts...
腿 手臂 甚至膝盖
legs, arms, even the knees.
但是没有一首赞美可怜的脚
But not one verse for the poor foot.
- 你认为是为什么?  - 因为顺序的关系吧
- Why do you think that is?  - Priorities, I suppose.
你能作得出来吗?
Did you think you would make one?
问题是没有字可以押韵
Problem is there's nothing to rhyme it with.
- 敲  - 那不是名词
- Put.  - It's not a noun.
没有关系 用力往地上敲...
Doesn't matter. Along he came and he did put...
是他笨重的脚
upon my farm his clumsy foot.
我们该说故事了
We should have a story now.
我在家说故事给我侄女听的时候...
When I tell a story to my nieces at home...
她们会有一个人先起头
one of them always provides the first sentence.
- 随便我们?  - 随便你们
- Anything?  - Absolutely anything.
有一个流浪的中国人 叫程欢...
There was a wandering Chinese named Cheng Huan...
住在伦敦的莱姆屋区...
living in Limehouse...
还有一个叫雪莉的女孩
and a girl named Shirley.
说着一口流利的中文...
Who spoke perfect Chinese...
是她传教的父母教她的
which she learned from her missionary parents.
程欢孤独地住在 福尔摩沙街上的蓝灯笼...
Cheng Huan lived alone in a room on Formosa Street...
楼上的房间里
above the Blue Lantern.
他坐在窗边...
He sat at his window...
思念的心中...
and in his poor listening heart...
回荡着故乡的声音...
strange echoes of his home and country...
第二天 他们被发现...
They found them there the next morning...
倒在蓝灯笼楼上的房间里...
in their room above the Blue Lantern...
死掉的孩子和那个军阀...
the dead child and the warlord...
脖子上还缠着程欢爱的礼物
with Cheng Huan's love gift coiled about his neck.
你去过那些地方吗?
Had you been to those places?
我向来喜欢神游
I have been a mental traveller.
- 一直到现在  - 对
- Till now.  - Yes.
这是英国故事? 还是丹麦?
Was this England? Excuse me. Denmark?
我喜欢自己的东西
I like my things.
你在神游的时候...
When you travelled before in your mind...
也带这么多行李吗?
did you carry so much luggage?
神游的人不会饿 不会累...
A mental traveller hasn't the need to eat or sleep...
也不需要宴客
or entertain.
你说得对
You're right.
难道你不高兴我带了 自己的水晶和瓷器来?
Anyway, aren't you pleased that I brought my crystal and china?
还有你的故事 对
And your stories, yes.
凯旋的英雄回来了
The conquering heroes come
嘹亮的号角
Sound the trumpets
激昂的鼓
Beat the drums
- 我希望你能常来  - 我也希望
- I want you to come often.  - I'd like that very much.
- 你一定要保证会尽快  - 我保证
- And you must promise it will be soon.  - I promise.
费奇哈顿 你救了我一命?
Did you save my life, Finch Hatton?
不是我 是那只狮子决定走开
No. The lioness did that. She walked away.
那我就没欠你什么了
So I'm not indebted, then?
但是我有
Ah, but I am.
在这里我们付钱请人说故事
We pay our storytellers here.
好漂亮
It's lovely.
可是我的故事不收钱...
But my stories are free...
而且你的礼物太贵重了
and your present's much too dear.
有空把它们写下来
Write them down sometime.
保重 费奇哈顿
Take care, Finch Hatton.
你为什么不叫我丹尼斯?
You wouldn't rather call me Denys?
男爵夫人
Baroness.
再见
Goodbye.
你在干嘛?
What are you doing?
我要你回家
I want you to come home.
我们从来没讨论过小孩的事
We never spoke about children.
你...
Did you...
你呢?
Do you?
想 可以吗?
Yes. Is that all right?
这些吉库犹人现在都想生病了
These Kikuyu want to be sick now.
老天爷
Good Lord.
你的腿伤恶化了
Your leg has got worse.
你必须去医院
You should go to hospital.
这只腿不太聪明
This leg may be foolish.
它可能不想去医院
It may think not to go to hospital.
随那只腿怎么想
This leg will do as it pleases.
但是如果你带它去医院...
But if you will take it to hospital...
我会认为你很聪明
I will think that you are wise.
像这样聪明的人 我会希望请他帮我做事...
And such a wise man as this, I would want to work in my house...
付他工钱
for wages.
像那样聪明的人可以赚多少钱?
How much wages would come to such a wise man as that?
比你放羊赚的钱要多
More wages than come from tending goats.
我会跟这只腿谈谈
I will speak to this leg.
- 空袭怎么办?  - 安静! 一个一个问
- What about air raids?  - Quiet! One question at a time.
战场是在欧洲 我们怎么知道不会蔓延到这边?
The war is in Europe. How do we know they're going to reach here?
往南方两百哩就是东德 赖托将军在那边
German East is only 200 miles south. General von Lettow is there.
我不希望在这里等他打过来
I don't want to wait until he joins us at the bar.
- 双方会交战吗?  - 毕斯 这是我们的事
- Would we engage them?  - Blix, this is our war.
你不需要淌这趟浑水
You don't have to be involved, but thanks.
我快要收成了 这场战争会持续多久?
I've got crops coming in. How long's this thing gonna last?
我们只有尽力撑下去
We just have to stay and go as we must.
不要轻举妄动就不会有事
They won't fight if we won't fight.
我们可以武装马萨伊人 对付德国佬
We could always arm the Masai and point them south.
事情结束以后 你要负责收回武器吗?
Do you want the job of collecting rifles from the Masai when this is over?
妇女和小孩怎么办? 该带他们进城来吗?
What about our women and children? Should we bring them into town?
有必要的时候再说
We will deal with that problem as it arises.
- 他们会用土著军队吗?  - 我想是会 但不是马萨伊人
- Will they use native troops?  - I'd assume so, but not Masai.
巴克利 你的索马里人呢?
Berkeley, what about your Somalis?
他们会是非常好的斥候 我们可以监视附近的区域
They'd make very good scouts. We could cover the area from here to the border.
还可以收集正规军到达的情报
We could gather information for when the regulars arrive.
到底怎么回事? 你清楚吗?
What's it about? Have you any idea?
- 不太清楚  - 那你干嘛淌这趟浑水?
- Not really.  - Then why do you want to get into it?
- 呃...  - 根本不关我们的事
- Well...  - It's got nothing to do with us.
我们不清楚他们之间的协议
They've made agreements we know nothing about.
拜托 维多利亚女王 和德国皇帝是亲戚
Victoria and the Kaiser were relatives, for God's sake.
他们私自划分了非洲 你知道为什么有边界?
They've divided Africa between them. Do you know why there's a border?
因为她有两座山 而他一座都没有
Because she had two mountains, and he had none.
所以她把吉力马扎罗山给他
So she gave him Kilimanjaro.
两个自私国家之间的愚蠢协议
It's a silly argument between two spoiled countries.
这场战争越快结束 生活就越快恢复正常
The sooner it ends, the sooner we pick up where we left off.
是会结束...
It may end...
但是不会回复到以前的生活
but we're not going to pick up where we left off.
你没有必要去
You don't have to go.
- 但是你想去  - 我们必须住在这里
- You want to go.  - We've got to live here.
他们说过不需要你帮忙
They have made it plain they don't want you.
- 我必须让他们知道我们的立场  - 我不是那么喜欢他们的国家
- I'll have to show them where we stand.  - I'm not so fond of their empire...
我会叫他们杀了你
I'd have you shot for it.
比起你来 他们不足为惧
More likely chewed on than shot.
农场不会有事的 有贝纳帮你
The farm will take care of itself, and you've got Belknap.
农场不会有事才怪
The farm will not take care of itself.
那不是重点
That's not the point.
我没有想过会这么喜欢你
I didn't expect to like you so much.
你不是开始谈恋爱了吧?
You're not going to go falling in love, are you?
不是爱上一个常常不在家的人
Not with someone who's always leaving.
需要我的话 就派信差来找狄米
If you need me, send a runner to find Delamere.
我会和他在一起
That's where I'll be.
很棒的吻别
That's a fine kiss goodbye.
我比较会说哈罗
I am better at hello.
道别是一种奇怪的感觉
It's an odd feeling... farewell.
中间搀杂着羡慕
There is some envy in it.
男人出去接受考验 磨练勇气
Men go off to be tested for courage.
而女人要接受的考验 却是磨练耐性...
If we're tested at all, it's for patience...
独自一个人...
for doing without...
学习如何面对寂寞
for how well we can endure loneliness.
其实我一直都明白
But I had always known that.
不需要这场战争
It didn't require a war.
我送走了波尔
I said goodbye to Bror.
丹尼斯没有道别就离开了...
Denys left without a word...
非常正确的作法
which was quite proper.
喂 那屋子!
Hello, the house!
菲莉丝!
Felicity!
我带了一些肉给你
I thought you might want some meat.
- 有什么消息吗?  - 没什么新消息
- Is there any word?  - No, nothing new.
没什么战况 只有可怕的热病
Not much fighting. Awful fever, though.
我可以留下来喝茶
I've got time for tea, I should think.
你支持德国吗?
Are you for the Germans?
他们派你来问我的?
Did they send you out to ask me this?
- 城里有一排的人  - 就因为我的破英文
- We had a row about it in town.  - Because of my bad English.
那你支持谁呢?
And whose side were you on?
你
Yours.
他们要送我回家上学 妈说我越来越野了
They want to send me home to school. Mother says I'm growing up wild.
- 我想问你的意见  - 问我?
- I wanted to ask you about it.  - Me?
你有过经验
You've been round and about.
有一天 我要像你一样 过自己要的生活
Someday, I'd like to run my own show the way you do.
- 我是这样的吗?  - 至少你不太需要我们
- Is that what I do?  - You don't seem to need us much.
男爵夫人 我可以问你一件事吗?
Baroness, may I ask you something?
我不太了解男人
I don't know much about men.
我希望他们喜欢我 但是...
I want them to like me, but I...
我也希望他们不要烦我
I want to be let alone too.
我应该被动 对不对?
I'm supposed to want to be taken, aren't I?
我有一本书
I've got this book.
但是你怎么知道什么时候该主动
But how do you know when to do what they want you to...
什么时候该被动?
and when not to?
我想你该叫我凯伦
I suppose you ought to call me Karen.
他们需要三百人份的石蜡 还有罐头食物
They need paraffin and tinned food, enough for 300 men.
他要你派个白人送蓬车过去
He wants you to send a white man with the wagon.
- 他没事吧?  - 可以送口信来就应该没事
- Is he all right?  - Well enough to send the message.
我丈夫要这辆蓬车送去哪?
And where would my husband like this wagon sent?
他和狄米在靠近内川湖的边界
He's with Delamere on the border near Lake Natron.
当然 那是机密
That's confidential, of course.
中尉 我会记住
I will bear that in mind, Lieutenant.
我只是不希望在奈洛比的人 知道这件事
I only meant it wouldn't do for it to be talk around Nairobi.
而且你必须搬到城里 我们没办法保护你
And we're going to have to move you into town. We can't protect you here.
什么意思?
What do you mean?
我们担心当地的土著 这是奉命行事
With the men gone, we're worried about the native element. We have orders.
妇女和小孩要搬到城里
Women and children into town.
中尉 你这是拘留
That is internment, Lieutenant.
妇女和小孩 男爵夫人
Women and children, Baroness.
- 分开算 还是一起算?  - 你会需要时间收拾东西
- Is that one category or two?  - You'll want time to gather your things.
星期四我会派一支护卫队来接你
I'll send an escort for you Thursday.
还有 我是上尉
And I'm a captain, Baroness.
我不是来打仗的 毕斯夫人 我知道
I'm not paid to fight, Mrs Blixen.
内川湖在哪?
Where is Lake Natron?
在南边 灌木区
It's south, bush country.
那不是白人去的地方
It's no place for a white man.
我们今天应该渡过沙河的
We should have crossed the Sand River today.
我可能带错路了
I may have got us lost.
夫人 神是全能的
God is great, msabu.
- 你跑来这里干嘛?  - 我要去找狄米
- What the devil are you doing here?  - I'm on my way to Delamere.
乱来 我们不派女人去打仗的
Ridiculous. We don't send women to war.
我要去
I'm going.
你连自己在哪都不知道
We haven't time for this. You don't even know where you are.
我现在知道了
I do now.
- 你只会再迷路  - 我还是要去
- You'll just get lost again.  - I'm going on.
- 你劝劝她 行不行?  - 不行
- Talk to her, will you?  - No.
- 她可能会受伤或者遇到危险  - 我想她知道
- She could be hurt or worse.  - I imagine she knows that.
行 我不管了
Right. I tried.
拿着
Here.
每天早上拿指南针 对着地平线上的一点
Find a spot on the horizon each morning and steer by it.
往西南走 大概三天
South, southwest. About three days.
我知道了
I see.
不用担心我们 我们不会有事的
Don't worry about us. We'll be all right.
- 那是什么?  - 马萨伊人
- What is it?  - Masai.
伊斯玛 我的枪 我的来福枪呢?
Ismail! My rifle! Where's my rifle?
滚开!
Get away!
夫人在流血 她并不拥有那头牛
Msabu's bleeding. She does not have this ox.
狮子肚子饿
This lion is hungry.
他不拥有那头牛
He does not have this ox.
蓬车非常重
This wagon is heavy.
它不拥有那头牛
It doesn't have this ox.
夫人 神在高兴
God is happy, msabu.
他开了我们玩笑
He plays with us.
告诉毕斯 他太太来了
Tell Blix his wife's here.
我带了些东西给你
I've brought you some things.
你换发型了
You've changed your hair.
- 你需要补给品  - 我说了派别人来
- You needed supplies.  - Send someone, I said.
能到得了算你命大
You were lucky to get through.
- 你实在是很大胆  - 但是我办到了
- It was really foolish.  - But I did get through.
而且很有意思
And it was fun.
你什么时候回家?
When are you coming home?
不
No.
还不是时候
Not just yet.
你不打算回农场帮忙 对不对?
You're not going to help at all with the farm.
我可以强迫你 可以不管你
I could force you. I could cut you off.
我只好靠打猎为生
I'll just hunt professionally.
反正我也喜欢
I might do it anyway.
事情和我们当初计划的不一样
It's not the way we thought it would be.
对吗?
Is it?
但是我喜欢你对我坦白
But I like it that you're honest with me.
我也喜欢你
I like you too.
非常喜欢
Very much.
丹尼斯给我一个指南针
I had a compass from Denys.
他说 用来指引方向
To steer by, he said.
但是后来我才明白
But later it came to me...
我们各有各的路要走
that we navigated differently.
也许他早就知道...
Perhaps he knew, as I did not...
地球之所以是圆的...
that the Earth was made round...
就是不要让我们太快知道结果
so that we would not see too far down the road.
你得了梅毒
You've got syphilis.
不可能
That's not possible.
你丈夫没生病?
Your husband is not ill?
我上次看到他是没有
Not the last time I saw him.
那是三个月前的事 他和...
That was three months ago. He's on the...
他和狄米在边界 有病他会回家的
He's on the border with Delamere. He would have come home.
每个病例不同
These cases vary.
他可能才刚被传染
He may have just a touch.
你的情况非常严重
You're very ill.
唯一的可能是他?
Is he the only possibility?
是
Yes.
你必须回家接受治疗
You'll have to go home to deal with it.
治疗起来很困难 但是他们有种药 叫撒尔佛散
The treatment's difficult, but they have a thing called salvarsan.
砒霜
Arsenic.
要是治不好...
And if I'm not cured...
病毒会侵害到脑部 对不对?
then I will be insane, won't I?
你应该尽快出发
You ought to go soon.
我必须帮你先生检查
I'll have to see your husband.
我会叫他来
I will send for him.
这些药在路上可以退烧
These ought to help with the fever till you get home.
我痊癒的机会有多少?
And what are my chances?
恐怕只有一半
About even, I'm afraid.
想不到这种事会发生在我身上
It's not what I thought would happen to me now.
- 什么?  - 夫人 你的信
- What?  - Your letters, msabu.
失陪一下
Excuse me.
我听说你办到了
I heard you'd made it.
我真希望看到他们脸上的表情
I'd have paid anything to see their faces.
- 一块喝杯饮料吧?  - 我还有事
- Would you join us for a drink?  - I can't.
一切都好吧?
How is it that you are home?
我把巴克利带回来了
I brought Berkeley back.
- 他受伤了吗?  - 热病
- Has he been wounded?  - Fever.
有点严重 但是他只要有琴酒就不会有事
More than usual, but he'll be all right as long as the gin holds out.
你呢? 战况如何?
And you? How is it with the fighting?
对方正在猛攻
We're taking a beating.
看样子不会太快结束
It's likely to last for a while.
- 你的指南针还在我这里  - 你为什么不留着?
- I still have your compass.  - Why don't you keep it?
是你应得的
You've earned it.
再说 我不是每次 都想知道自己去哪
Besides, I don't always want to know where I'm going.
我不打扰你了
Please don't let me keep you.
- 你没事吧?  - 没事 保重
- Are you all right?  - Yes. Take good care.
- 我们落后一两个故事  - 对 等我回来
- We're behind a story or two.  - Yes. When I get back.
回来? 你要去哪?
Back? From where?
我是说 等你回来
When you get back, I meant.
- 我以为是疟疾  - 嗯 可惜不是
- I thought it was malaria.  - Well, it wasn't.
你可能没事 不过还是要看医生
You may be all right, but you have to be seen.
还有其他人 不管她们是谁
And the others, whoever they are.
我希望她们都生病
I hope they've got it.
是我的错 不关别人的事
It's my fault. No one else's.
我和你一起回去
I want to go with you.
不行 必须有人留下来看着
No. Someone has to stay here and run things.
而且工厂必须要盖好
And the factory must be finished.
- 你能留下来吗?  - 不然怎么办
- Can you do that?  - That's little enough.
对不起
I'm sorry.
夫人呢?
Where is memsahib?
她很快就会来
She can come soon enough.
稍候 我出发前往蒙巴萨...
Later that day, I left for Mombasa...
然后搭船返回丹麦
and the voyage home to Denmark.
这是一趟漫长的旅程
It was a longer journey this time.
战事持续的进行
The war went on.
我在打一场属于自己的战争
I fought my own war.
砒霜是我的盟友...
Arsenic was my ally...
对抗我从未见过的敌人
against an enemy I never saw.
我待在我的故乡...
I stayed in the room where I was born...
我出生的房间...
in Rungstedland...
试着记起非洲的样子
and tried to remember the colours of Africa.
生活中只有药物...
There was only the medicine...
在荒芜的海滩上...
and walks with my mother...
和母亲一同漫步...
along a deserted stretch of beach...
以及母亲家中的房间
and this room in my mother's house.
丹麦让我觉得陌生...
Denmark had become a stranger to me...
反之亦然
and I to her.
但母亲的家让我感到熟悉
But my mother's house I came to know again.
我知道我会再回去...
And knew I would come back to it...
不论是否健康...
sick or well...
精神是否健全
sane or mad someday.
所以在察沃之后...
And so I did...
我回去了
after Tsavo.
现在几乎每个人都有一部
Almost everyone's got them now.
我现在是厨师了 夫人
I am cooking now, memsahib.
我听说了
Yes, I have heard about this.
你好吗 法拉?
Are you well, Farah Aden?
夫人 我很好
I am well enough, msabu.
那我也很好
Then I am well enough also.
- 你打算做什么?  - 我在想我会打猎
- What will you do?  - I have been thinking I'll hunt.
狩猎之类的
Safari sort of thing.
他们说等到战争结束 这会是不错的生意
They say it'll be quite a business once the war is over.
你不会想教书罗?
You wouldn't want to teach?
我希望这些吉库犹人能上学
I would like these Kikuyu to have a school.
那会引起很大的争议
There will be a fight about that.
你完全好了吗?
Are you all well?
他们说我痊癒了
They say I'm cured.
只是不会有小孩
I won't have children.
你有没有想过我们的事?
Have you thought about us?
当然有
Of course.
贝纳说再下一次雨 咖啡树就会开花
Belknap says the coffee will flower after the next rains.
是的话...
If it does...
你就要开始考虑请人来收成...
you'll have start thinking about hiring for the harvest...
还有怎么卖到市场去
and how you'll get to market.
- 巴克利会在哪?  - 他应该在这里
- Where would Berkeley be?  - He must be here.
谁赢了?
Who won the match?
有什么好听的故事吗?
Have you got a story for me?
我被降级了 你上次还叫我丹尼斯的
I've been demoted. I was Denys last time.
要不要来一点香槟?
Would you care for some champagne?
他们说你回去待了一阵
They said you went home for a while.
对 巴克利人呢?
Yes. Where is Berkeley?
真高兴看到你
It's good to see you.
他还在生病 不会有事的
He's still down with fever. He'll be all right.
这些人是谁?
Who are all these people?
波尔说 我们很快就会变殖民地
Bror says we'll be a colony soon.
对 他们希望解决这个问题
Yes. They want it settled now.
有一种抽奖办法 买一张彩票 就有机会在非洲赢到一座农场
There's a lottery. Buy a ticket, win a farm in Africa.
你真的认为一切都不会改变吗?
Did you really think it would stay the way it was?
我认为会
I thought it might.
- 卡努西亚呢?  - 他死了
- Where is Kanuthia?  - He's dead.
你好吗? 要不要一块喝一杯?
How are you? Would you join us for a drink?
我该回去休息了
It's time to find a pillow.
- 那改天?  - 好
- Another night then?  - Yeah.
圣诞快乐
Have a good Christmas.
圣诞节
Christmas.
难怪
So it is.
酋长说 超过这个高度的小孩...
This Chief says children higher than this...
就不可以上学
must not learn to read.
告诉他所有的小孩都应该上学
Tell him all the children must go to school.
不行 那是酋长
No. This is a chief.
- 你不是酋长  - 太可笑了
- You are not a chief.  - That's absurd.
不应该让高的人比这个酋长聪明
It's not good for tall people to know more than this chief.
这些小孩长高的时候...
When these children are tall...
这个酋长也差不多了
then this chief can be dead.
波尔还好 但是丹尼斯当向导的样子? 我不能想像
Bror, yes. But Denys hired out to tourists? I can't imagine.
他没有其他的专长 再说 我们别无选择
He's got no other trade. Besides, we've got no choice.
政府禁止猎象牙
The government's put a stop to the ivory.
- 你有什么打算?  - 我打算专心经营农场
- What will you do?  - I'll concentrate on the farm.
嘿 有人在吗!
Hello, the house!
菲莉丝 你什么时候回来的?
Felicity! How is it you're home?
我不回去了 你看
I'm out. Look.
我什么都没学到 但是也没染上恶习
I didn't learn a thing, but I'm wonderfully clean.
我会来看你 巴克利 你要请我跳舞
I'll come see you. You save me a dance, Berkeley.
我听说的学校是怎么回事?
What's this nonsense I hear about a school?
我请了一位年轻的传教士
I've taken on a young missionary.
他答应我先教字母表 后教圣经故事
He's promised me to do the alphabet first and save God for later.
他们连羊都不会数
Wogs can't even count their goats.
- 关你什么屁事  - 你是什么东西?
- It's none of your business.  - Who the devil are you?
可以请你跳支舞吗?
I wonder if you'd dance with me?
你应该道歉
You are about to apologize.
男爵夫人 你可真会搅局
You do stir things up, Baroness.
你怎么知道他们想上学的?
When they said they liked to read, how did they put that, exactly?
他们喜欢狄更斯吗?
Do they know they'd like Dickens?
- 你不认为他们该上学?  - 我认为你该先问他们
- You don't think they should learn?  - I think you might have asked them.
你小时候是自愿上学的吗?
Did you ask to learn when you were a child?
故事不可能对他们有害?
How can stories possibly harm them?
他们有自己的故事 只是没有写下来而已
They have their own stories. They're just not written down.
你凭什么要他们无知?
And what stake to you have in keeping them ignorant?
他们不是无知
They're not ignorant.
我只是不认为他们该变成英国人
I just don't think they should be turned into little Englishmen.
- 你喜欢改变事情  - 希望变得更好
- You do like to change things.  - For the better, I hope.
我要我的吉库犹人识字
I want my Kikuyu to learn to read.
"我的吉库犹人" "我的瓷器" "我的农场"
"My Kikuyu." "My Limoges." "My farm."
你不累吗
It's a lot to own.
那都是我努力得来的
I have paid a price for everything I own.
什么才是你的?
What is it, exactly, that's yours?
这一切都不属于我们 我们只是过客
We're not owners here. We're just passing through.
生活对你而言就这么简单吗?
Is life really so damn simple for you?
也许是因为我要求的不多
Perhaps I ask less of it than you do.
- 可惜我不相信  - 新年快乐!
- I don't believe that.  - Happy new year!
过去的老友将被遗忘
Should auld acquaintance be forgot
从此不再想起
And never brought to mind
过去的老友将被遗忘
Should auld acquaintance be forgot
为了美好的昔日
For the sake of auld lang syne
亲爱的 为美好的昔日
For auld lang syne, my dear
为美好的昔日
For auld lang syne
我们再饮一杯
We'll drink a cup of kindness here
为了美好的昔日
For the sake of auld lang syne
我们再饮一杯
We'll drink a cup
天佑...
God save...
吾皇
Our gracious king
愿他万寿无疆
Long live our noble king
天佑吾皇
God save our king
赐他胜利
Send him victorious
快乐和荣耀
Happy and glorious
凯伦 新年快乐
Happy new year, Karen.
你也一样
And for you too.
天佑吾皇
God save the king
有人的内衣忘记在后座
Someone has left her underclothes in the back.
我要你搬到城里住
I want you to take a place in town.
你确定?
Are you sure?
吃
Eat.
大象
Elephant.
给我事做
Give me work.
现在太平了 可是经济呢?
We've got peace. Where is the prosperity?
为什么不打仗了 价钱反而一落千丈?
Why should prices fall now just because we're not killing anybody?
茶叶的价钱也很惨
Well, tea's down just as bad.
非要这么用力抽它们不行吗?
Do they always have to whip them so?
你看 他们终于发明了 一部有用的机器
Look. They finally made a machine that's really useful.
你听
Listen.
是给你的
It's for you.
- 我不能接受  - 为什么?
- I can't accept it.  - Why not?
波尔搬到城里了
Bror's moved to town.
我想我无权过问
That's a private matter, I imagine.
你会留下来过夜吗?
Did you think you would spend the night?
不会 我必须去马拉一趟
Can't, thanks. I have to go down to the Mara.
我接了向导的工作 必须去找一块营地
I've taken up safari work, and I've got to find a camp.
你应该去那边看看
There's country there you ought to see.
不然就没机会了
It won't last long now.
我只会浪费你的时间
No. I would be wasting your time.
不如你去收拾一下?
Why don't you get your things?
你要是喜欢我...
If you like me at all...
就不要叫我去
don't ask me to do this.
你是怎么说的?
What's your word?
嘘?
Shoo?
是不是? 嘘?
Is that it? Shoo?
这个字还真有用 男爵夫人
That's a fine word you've got there, Baroness.
再转一次 好吗?
Crank it again, will you?
还差一点 再转一次
Almost. Crank it again.
再转
Again.
再一次
Once more.
做得好 我们出发
Well done. We're off.
我是没有办法解释...
I don't know the scientific basis for it...
但是我知道在非洲看星星 比其他地方都清楚
but I know you can see further in the African night than any other place.
而且星星特别亮
And the stars are brighter.
是帐蓬的关系
It's about the tents.
我和卡努西亚一起的时候...
When I'm out with Kanuthia...
以前一起的时候 根本不用他们
it used to be we didn't use them.
我记得他
I remember him.
说不出来是...
There was something...
马萨伊人
Masai.
他有一半的血统 所以你特别记得他
He was half Masai. That's what you remember about him.
他们不像其他人
They're like nobody else.
我们以为能教化他们...
We think we'll tame them...
结果不能
but we won't.
要是把他们关进监狱 他们会死
If you put them in prison, they die.
- 为什么?  - 因为他们活在现在
- Why?  - Because they live now.
他们不担心未来
They don't think about the future.
他们不能忍受被排除在外的感觉
They can't grasp the idea that they'll be let out one day.
他们不知道只是暂时的
They think it's permanent.
所以他们会死
So they die.
他们是唯一不在乎我们的部落...
They're the only ones out here that don't care about us...
那也是他们的致命伤
and that is what will finish them.
你们都谈些什么呢?
What did the two of you ever find to talk about?
什么都不谈
Nothing.
所以 你知道我会来
So. You knew I would come.
去休息吧 明天还要早起?
It's an early day tomorrow. Why don't you get some sleep?
- 明天要干嘛?  - 我不知道
- And what happens tomorrow?  - I have no idea.
- 晚安  - 晚安
- Good night.  - Good night.
你认为它们会吓跑
You would think they would run off.
你不认为
You didn't.
想想看
Think of that.
它们第一次听到莫扎特的音乐
Never a man-made sound, and then Mozart.
- 你有客户了吗?  - 下星期
- Have you clients already?  - In a week.
一个比利时人和他的女儿
A man from Belgium and his daughters.
他信上说 "我们要三人份的行程"
His letter said, "We'd like three of everything."
会是一趟有趣的旅行 我会去一个月...
It'll be an interesting trip. I'll be gone a month...
或者一个半小时
or an hour and a half.
你为何选择这种行业?
Why are you doing this?
我不会缝衣服
I don't know how to sew.
你知道那是用什么做的? 布料
Do you know what they're made of? Cloth.
他要在哪降落?
Where will he land?
秘决是不要想
Trick is not to.
感觉一定很棒
It must feel amazing.
那是我想像中美国的样子
It's how I imagined America to be.
- 你去过美国吗?  - 没去过 我父亲去过
- Have you been to America?  - No, but my father was there.
我小时候他告诉我许多美国的事
He told me stories about it when I was a little girl.
- 你们还这么亲吗?  - 他去世了
- Are you still close?  - He died.
我十岁的时候 他自杀了
He killed himself when I was ten years old.
我想 我有办法
I can fix that, I think.
"放声大笑...
"Laughed loud and long...
他的眼光同时四处环顾
and all the while his eyes went to and fro.
他说 '哈 我看到全部的平原
'Ha ha,' quoth he, 'full plain I see.
魔鬼知道该如何争执'
The devil knows how to row.'
- 再见 再见..."  - 你漏了好几句
- Farewell, farewell..."  - You're skipping verses.
我是故意跳过的
I leave out the dull parts.
"再见 再见...
"Farewell, farewell...
我告诉你们这些婚礼的宾客"
but this I tell to thee, thou wedding guest."
头往后仰
Lay your head back.
"他虔诚的祈祷...
"He prayeth well...
热爱所有的人和鸟类...
who loveth well both man and bird...
以及野兽"
and beast."
这样好多了
That's better.
这和受雇狩猎有什么不同?
Will it be so different, hunting for hire?
对动物来说没有 说不定有
Not for the animals. Well, maybe for the animals.
你真的宁愿和它们为伍?
Do you really prefer them to people?
有时候
Sometimes.
它们不像人虚情假意
They don't do anything half-heartedly.
认真对待每一件事...
Everything's for the first time...
猎食 工作 交配
Hunting, working, mating.
只有人类才会乱来
It's only man that does it badly.
只有人才会没耐性
It's only man that tires of going through it.
人说 我知道你对我的感觉...
Who says, "See here. Now I know how you feel about me...
你也知道我对你的感觉...
and you know how I feel about you...
既然我们互相了解 不如上床吧"
and we understand each other, so let's lie down and get on with it."
你为何带我来这里?
Why am I here?
因为我要你看这些
Because I wanted you to see all this.
我要带你来看
I wanted to show it to you.
我觉得你会明白
I thought you'd understand it.
你想过死亡吗?
Do you think much about death?
我想过老化的问题
I think about getting old.
就像和古怪的老头子住在一起
Be like living with a cranky, demanding old bastard.
你就是一个古怪的老头子
Well, you are a cranky, demanding old bastard.
我得过梅毒
I had syphilis.
那就是我回家的原因
That's why I went home.
我知道
I know.
我好像从来不生病
I never seem to get anything.
出过一次德国麻疹
German measles once.
他们说我会有正常的生活...
They say I'll have a normal life now...
只是不会有小孩
but no children.
学校?
So, the school?
学校
So, the school.
农场 那些是我生命的全部
The farm. That's what I am now.
明天露营会需要肉类
We'll need meat for the camp tomorrow.
黎明的时候我会叫你
I'll wake you at dawn.
晚安
Good night.
我们可能会遇到猩猩 但是会再进入水牛的聚集地
We might scare up gazelles, but we'll be going through buffalo country again.
我们徒步的时候 他们变得很大胆
They get cocky when you're on foot.
晚餐
Supper.
个头不错 但是...
Good size, but...
狮子
Lion.
小心 我们在顺风处
Careful, the wind's behind us.
后退
Back up.
慢慢的
Slowly.
如果它冲过来 别动...
If there's a charge, drop flat...
让我来处理
and let me do it.
重新上膛!
Reload!
准备晚餐了吗?
Dinner in a while?
我很高兴你来了
I'm glad you came.
敬玫瑰唇少女
To rose-lipped maidens.
有个从丹麦来的年轻女孩...
There was a very young girl from Denmark...
坐上前往苏伊士的汽船
who took passage on a steamer bound for Suez.
一场风暴...
There was a storm...
从摩洛哥吹来...
off Morocco...
她被冲到岸边...
and she was washed ashore...
到沙滩上
onto a beach.
到白沙沙滩上
Onto a white beach.
一个沙滩 如此洁白...
Onto a beach so, so white...
我愿意这么做
I'd like to do that.
- 还痛吗?  - 不痛
- Will that hurt?  - No.
你现在说什么我都会相信
If you say anything now, I'll believe it.
我需要知道如何看待这件事
I need to know how to think about this.
为什么?
Why?
清汤 莴苣...
Your clear soup, the new lettuce...
鸡肉 只要鸡胸肉
chicken, just the breast.
我相信这些对你没有问题?
I trust this meets with your approval?
- 谁要来?  - 柯尔老板要来
- Who is coming?  - Bwana Cole is coming.
我会让他满意的
I will think on Bwana Cole.
我让自己陷入了更大的麻烦
I've got myself in real trouble now.
- 你认为他们该有投票权?  - 不是 更糟
- Now you think they should vote?  - No, worse.
叫卡曼来
Get Kamante.
他越来越不像话
He is out of hand entirely.
这看起来像鸡肉吗?
Does this look like a chicken?
这里不是鸡肉 夫人 这里是鱼肉
Here is not a chicken, memsahib. Here is a fish.
走开
Go away.
你觉得如何?
What do you think?
相当可口 对不对?
It's quite good, isn't it?
小心
Be careful.
以前的制图师到世界边缘的时候 总写下...
When the old map makers got to the edge of the world, they used to write...
"越过此界有龙出没"
"Beyond this place there be dragons."
这是我现在的处境吗?
Is that where I am?
他喜欢给礼物...
He likes to give presents...
但不是在圣诞节
but not at Christmas.
他甚至没说他何时会回来
He hasn't even said when he's coming again.
要是他再来的话
If he's coming again.
你会离婚吗?
Would you divorce?
那我就什么都没有了
Then I would have no one.
没猎到阿拉斯加糜鹿...
Men who missed moose in Alaska...
美洲灰熊 印度老虎的人...
grizzly in America, tiger in India...
现在都在海上 朝这里航行
are all at sea now, bound for here.
巴克利要经营农场
Berkeley is going to farm.
你也可以
You could do that.
不 谢了
No, thank you.
你该去看看他
You ought to look in on him, though.
他看起来不太好
He didn't look all that well.
你可以留下来吗?
Can you stay?
一两天吧
For a day or so.
- 够吗?  - 不够
- Is that all right?  - No.
一趟狩猎不需要两个向导
You don't need two guns on safari.
那做文书的工作
Then do the town work.
见见客户 准备行头
Meet the clients, do outfitting, there's mail.
我不认为我适合
I don't know that I'd be right for that.
你必须找点事做
You've got to do something.
其实 我不必找
I don't, actually.
我的小便开始变黑了
My water's gone black.
我们必须送你去医院 让你接受适当的照顾
We've got to get you to a hospital and get you some proper care.
我被照顾的很好
I'm being cared for properly.
已经...
It's...
好多年了
some years now.
我认为 她喜欢我
She's fond of me, I think.
你为何不告诉我?
Why didn't you tell me?
我以为...
I suppose...
我认为...
I thought...
我对你的了解不够深
I didn't know you well enough.
帐户里还有一点钱
There's money left in the trading account.
把我的份给玛亚莫
I'd like my share to go to Mairiamo.
听着
Listen.
乔治马丁得了黑尿热病 过了五年都没事
George Martin had black water fever, and that was five years now.
你可以拿走你喜欢的那把猎枪
You might take along that 12-bore you're so fond of.
扳机好像有点...
The trigger seems a bit...
让凯伦试那把瑞比猎枪
Get Karen to try the Rigby.
那把大小刚好适合她
It's a nice-size gun for her.
你要...
Would you like...
你要我带你回家吗?
Would you like me to take you home?
我想我到家了
I am home, I suppose.
- F  - F
- "F."  - "F."
- G  - G
- "G."  - "G."
G代表女孩
"G" for girl.
你打包好了吗?
Are you packed?
好了
Yes.
城里怎么样?
How was town?
热闹
Crowded.
我一直在想
I've been thinking.
现在我在俱乐部的房间...
With all the safari work, I have little use for the room...
几乎用不到
at the club.
我不知道这样说恰不恰当...
I don't know that I'd be any good at this...
如果我把东西留在你那里行吗?
but how would it be if I kept a few things with you?
你会把我家当歇脚处?
You would come and go from my house?
你不介意的话
If that's all right.
神要惩罚你的时候 他会应允你的祷告
When the gods want to punish you, they answer your prayers.
巴克利快死了
Berkeley's dying.
- 什么?  - 黑尿热病
- What?  - Black water fever.
我的天
Oh, my God.
- 我要去看他  - 不 他不希望你去
- I'll go to him.  - No, he wouldn't want you there.
为什么?
Why?
有个女人在 她是索马里人
There's a woman there. She's Somali.
他们在一起有一段时间了
She's been with him for some time.
你从来没告诉过我
You never told me this.
我也不知道
I didn't know.
"和我们每个人永远同在" 阿门
"with each one of us now and forevermore." Amen.
丹尼斯竟然会没来
Strange that Denys isn't here.
我想他正在怀念巴克利
I think he is off with Berkeley.
丹尼斯在家的时候...
In the days and hours that Denys was at home...
我们都聊些奇特的见闻
we spoke of nothing ordinary.
不谈农场那些麻烦事...
Not of my troubles with the farm...
我到期的贷款和欠收的农作物...
my notes due and my failing crop...
不谈他的工作...
or of his, with his work...
非洲发生的事
what he knew was happening to Africa.
或者任何生活中的琐事
Or of anything at all that was small and real.
我们过着与世隔绝...
We lived disconnected...
与世无争的生活
and apart from things.
他不在的时候 我编写了许多的故事
I had been making up stories while he was away.
到了夜晚 他在火炉前...
In the evenings, he made himself comfortable...
舒服的靠在垫子上
spreading cushions like a couch in front of the fire.
而我则盘着双腿...
And with me sitting cross-legged like Shahrazade herself...
让他聚精会神的听我说故事...
he would listen, clear eyed, to a long tale...
从头详细的说起
from when it began until it ended.
你从哪弄来的?
Where did you get it?
蒙巴萨
Mombasa.
上来
Get in.
你何时学会开飞机的?
When did you learn to fly?
昨天
Yesterday.
别动
Don't move.
我想要动
I want to move.
别动
Don't move.
恬妮 可以和你谈谈吗?
Tanne, may I see you?
其实 我的手头也很紧 知道不?
Well, I'm broke too, you know?
要不是小费收入不好 我不会向你开口的
I wouldn't ask, but tips were a bit light.
- 你还好吧?  - 如果收成好的话
- Are you all right?  - If I get a decent crop.
我可以开枪打他
I could shoot him.
我有股吻你的冲动
I've got this terrible urge to kiss you.
他比我聪明
He is smarter than I am.
也许会很顺利
It may go well.
祝你好运 恬妮
Good luck, Tanne.
你应该先问一声
You might have asked.
我有
I did.
她说好
She said yes.
哪一天万一我被吃掉了 记得把我埋在这里 好吗?
If I get eaten up some time, bury me here, will you?
所有剩下的部分
Whatever's left.
就是那里 山脊上面
Just there, at the crest of the hill.
你何时出发?
When are you leaving?
明天
Tomorrow.
你不介意我是别人的妻子吗?
Doesn't it matter to you that I'm another man's wife?
我只在意你所做的努力
What matters to me is that you tried so hard.
明天什么时候?
What time tomorrow?
再见
Goodbye again.
耕地有多少英亩?
How many acres under cultivation?
- 五百亩  - 其他都是荒地?
- Five hundred.  - The rest of it's wild?
- 吉库犹人住在那里  - 为什么不赶他们走?
- Well, the Kikuyu live there.  - Why don't you move them off?
因为他们住在那里
'Cause they live there.
万一不能履行契约 土地就会被接收
We'll take it over should you default.
- 又延长了一年  - 神是全能的
- We've got another year.  - God is great, msabu.
他收百分之三的利息
He's charging three percent.
这个酋长说...
This chief says...
高的小孩可以来上学
tall children can come to school now.
告诉酋长 读书是一件重要的事
Tell Chief Kinanjui that reading is a valuable thing.
他的族人会永远感激他的
His children will remember him well.
这个酋长说 "英国人也识字 他们有多好?"
This chief says, "British can read, and what good has it done them?"
菲莉丝史威小姐 完美的表现
Miss Felicity Spurway, clear round.
她真的很厉害
She's quite something, that Felicity.
没错
Yes, indeed.
下一位参赛者 约翰苏顿先生
The next competitor, Mr John Sutton on Castano.
你好吗?
How are you?
开始老了
Getting old, I think.
你呢?
Not you.
生意好吗?
How is the hunt?
够我生活 丹尼斯呢?
I'll make a living. Where is Denys?
在乌干达 某个部落
Uganda. Some potentate.
我想你可能会要离婚
I thought you might be wanting a divorce.
她有钱吗?
Has she got money?
她当然有钱
Of course she's got money.
这重要吗?
Is this important?
我想是吧!
I suppose.
那我必须找理由指控你
Well, I'll have to accuse you of something.
还是你来指控我?
Or did you think you would have it the other way around?
尽快就好 我无所谓
Fire away. Whatever.
这是我应得的
I have surely done it.
谢谢你 恬妮
Thank you, Tanne.
你是如何让我们还像... 朋友一样?
How do you manage it... to keep us friends?
我们本来就是
We started that way.
我会替你高兴 如果我可以的话
Well, I'll be happy for you, if I can.
我一直记得
I remember that quite well.
你出去向导的时候...
When you go away on safari...
你和别人在一起过吗?
are you ever with someone else?
我只想和你一起
I'd be with you if I wanted to be with anyone.
- 你不会寂寞吗?  - 偶尔会
- Do you ever get lonely?  - Sometimes.
有没有想过我会不会寂寞?
Do you ever wonder if I am lonely?
不 没有
No, I don't.
你会想到我吗?
Do you think about me at all?
- 常常  - 但是不会想到要回来
- Often.  - But not enough to come back.
我有回来 每次都回来 怎么回事?
I do come back... all the time. What is it?
没事
Nothing.
波尔要求离婚 他找到新对象了
Bror has asked me for a divorce. He found someone that he wants to marry.
我只是以为我们也会
I just thought we might do that someday.
离婚?
Divorce?
结... 不结婚有这么大的差别吗?
How... How would a wedding change things?
我会有一个属于我的人
I would have someone of my own.
你不会
You wouldn't.
结婚到底有什么不好?
What's wrong with marriage, anyway?
你有看过成功的例子吗?
Have you ever seen one you admire?
有 看过很多
Yes, I have. Many.
贝菲家就是一个
Belfields, for one.
他在1910年雨季的时候 送她回娘家
He sent her home for the rains in 1910.
到1913年才告诉她 婚姻结束了
Didn't tell her they were over till 1913.
这不是个笑话 大家都结婚 又不是新发明
It's not a joke. People marry. It's not revolutionary.
- 有许多动物相守一辈子  - 鹅
- There are animals that mate for life.  - Geese.
你争论的时候 就可以用动物来举例
You use the damn animals for your own argument.
可是我要用就不行
You won't let me use them for mine.
我会守着我的伴侣
I'd mate for life.
一天一天过下去
One day at a time.
我只想有人向我求一次婚 如此而已
I'd just like someone to ask me once, that's all.
如果我保证拒绝你 你肯不肯问一次?
Promise me you'll do that, if I promise to say no?
相信你?
Just trust you, eh?
你出外的时候...
When you go away...
不是每次都去狩猎 对不对?
you don't always go on safari, do you?
只是想要离开
Just want to be away.
我不想让你难过
It's not meant to hurt you.
我是难过
It does.
我和你在一起是我的选择
I'm with you because I choose to be with you.
我不要按照别人的想法来过生活
I don't want to live someone else's idea of how to live.
不要勉强我
Don't ask me to do that.
我不希望有一天 发现自己是在帮别人活
I don't want to find out one day that I'm at the end of someone else's life.
我愿意承担后果 就算偶尔寂寞
I'm willing to pay for mine. To be lonely sometimes.
甚至孤独而终 我都能接受
To die alone, if I have to. I think that's fair.
不是这样 你是强迫我付出代价
Not quite. You want me to pay for it as well.
不 你有权选择 而且你不愿意为我牺牲
No, you have a choice, and you're not willing to do the same for me.
我不会因为一张纸...
I won't be closer to you...
和你更亲近或者更爱你
and I won't love you more because of a piece of paper.
看能不能堵住
See if you can shore it up.
快走
Move away.
算了
Let it go.
反正这些水住在蒙巴萨
This water lives in Mombasa anyway.
我飞到了纳拉克
I flew as far as Narok.
看到运货卡车驶过的车轮痕迹
You could see all the ruts where the lorries had been.
塞伦加提区还没有受影响
The Serengeti was still good.
到那里要一个星期
Take a week just getting there.
萨布拉区也没有受影响
And Samburu is still good.
贝纳人呢? 一直没看到他
Where's Belknap? I haven't seen him.
他现在应该在美国
He must be in America by now.
我让他走了
I let him go.
我没有选择 你是不是对农场的事没兴趣?
I had to. But you don't want to hear about the farm, do you?
- 你... 有扣子吗?  - 你在干嘛?
- L... Have you got any buttons?  - What are you doing?
- 帮你缝扣子  - 不必
- Mending your shirt.  - Don't.
不要缝
Don't do that.
你不需要这么做
You don't have to do that.
也许我后天再去萨布拉
Maybe I'll try Samburu day after tomorrow.
你才刚回来
You just got back.
菲莉丝要求和我一起去...
You know, Felicity asked to come along...
我打算拒绝她 因为知道你会不高兴
and I almost said no because I thought you wouldn't like it.
- 没有理由不让她来  - 有 我会不高兴
- There's no reason for her not to come.  - Yes, there is. I wouldn't like it.
你希望她去吗?
You want her along?
我希望不相干的事不要扯在一起
I want things that don't matter not to matter.
- 那为我就拒绝她  - 然后你又会有什么要求?
- Then tell her no. Do it for me.  - And then? What else would it be?
为什么你的自由就比我的重要?
Why is your freedom more important that mine?
没有 而且我从来 不干涉你的自由
It isn't. And I've never interfered with your freedom.
我只是不可以需要你
No. I'm not allowed to need you.
依赖你 或者对你有所期待
Or rely on you, or expect anything from you.
我随时可以离开
I'm free to leave.
- 但是我需要你  - 你不需要我
- But I do need you.  - You don't need me.
我死了你就会死吗? 你不需要我
If I die, will you die? You don't need me.
你只是搞混了 你分不清需要和占有
You're confused. You've mixed up need with want. You always have.
我的天 你理想的世界 绝对不会有爱的存在
My God. In the world that you would make, there would be no love at all.
只有最伟大的 不需要去证明的那种
Or the best kind. The kind we wouldn't have to prove.
- 那你干脆住到月球上  - 为什么? 就因为我不照你的意思?
- You'll be living on the moon then.  - Why? Because I won't do it your way?
难道就只能照你的方法吗?
Are we assuming there's one proper way to do all this?
你认为我在乎菲莉丝?
Do you think I care about Felicity?
认为我会和她有关系?
Do you think I'll be involved with her?
- 那就没有必要这样做  - 如果她不重要...
- Then there's no reason for this.  - If she's not important...
那你在坚持什么?
why won't you give it up?
我学到你没学到的经验
I have learned a thing that you haven't.
有些东西值得拥有...
There are some things worth having...
但是要付出代价 而我就是其中之一
but they come at a price, and I want to be one of them.
我不答应
I won't allow it.
你不知道这句话 对我的影响有多大
You have no idea the effect that language has on me.
我一直以为你什么都不要...
I used to think that there was nothing that you really wanted...
其实不是 对不对?
but that's not it, is it?
你什么都想要
You want to have it all.
我要去萨布拉 她来不来随她
I'm going to Samburu. She can come or not.
那你就去别的地方住
Then you will be living elsewhere.
好
All right.
有白马王子吗?
Is that a prince in there?
夫人 你最好快点来
I think that you had better get up, memsahib.
- 什么?  - 你最好快点来看
- What?  - I think that you had better get up.
我想神来了
I think that God is coming.
全没了
All gone.
- 怎么发生的?  - 我想是神的杰作
- How did it start?  - I think God had a hand in it.
他想起来他给了我 有史以来最好的收成
He gave me my best crop ever, and then He remembered.
- 保险呢?  - 悲观的人才需要买
- Insurance?  - That's for pessimists.
丹尼斯呢?
Where is Denys?
谁知道
Who knows?
无所谓了 狄米 男爵夫人破产了
Doesn't matter. The baroness is broke, "D."
一切都结束了
It's over.
在回去之前 我必须帮 我的吉库犹人找地方安身
I've got to find some land before I go, for my Kikuyu.
凯伦 你的麻烦够多了
You've trouble enough, Karen.
随便哪都行 只要他们能在一起
Just a chunk somewhere, so they can stay all together.
我们刚好没有咖啡了...
We're just out of coffee...
但是我可以请你喝茶
but I can give you tea.
保留区外没有那么大块的可耕地...
There is no arable land that size outside the reserve...
就算有 我们也不会给土著
and if there were, we'd not put natives on it.
- 就算是他们的土地  - 现在属于英国皇室了
- Since it's theirs.  - It belongs to the crown, Baroness.
你的要求根本是不可能
What you want is quite impossible.
向来如此 下一个我该找谁?
Yes, it always is. Who must I see next?
恐怕你能找的人都找遍了
You've run through us all, I'm afraid.
我们是不是有新总督了?
We have a new governor, haven't we?
乔瑟夫爵士? 他还没到
Sir Joseph? He hasn't arrived yet.
但是我听说快到了
But will soon, I'm told.
你在打听消息吗?
You do still ask me to things?
雅各鲁林上尉
Captain Jacques Llewllyn.
- 阁下  - 上尉
- Your servant, sir.  - Mr Llewllyn.
可敬的狄米领主
The honourable Hugh Chomondeley, Lord Delamere.
- 阁下  - 狄米领主
- Your servant, sir.  - Lady Delamere.
- 你好吗?  - 狄米夫人
- How do you do?  - Lady Delamere.
- 行政官  - 男爵夫人
- Commissioner.  - Baroness.
毕斯男爵夫人
The Baroness von Blixen.
我很遗憾你要离开肯尼亚
I'm sorry to know that Kenya will be losing you.
- 想必你听说了我的事?  - 是的
- You have heard of my trouble then?  - Yes.
我很遗憾
I regret it.
- 你一定知道我的处境?  - 男爵夫人
- And do you know of my problem now?  - Baroness.
- 你要求的这块地  - 你能帮我吗 乔瑟夫爵士?
- This land you want from us.  - Will you help me, Sir Joseph?
- 夫人 现在不是时候  - 实在是相当的困难
- Baroness, this really isn't the time.  - That's quite difficult.
- 男爵夫人  - 请你站起来
- Baroness.  - Please, get up.
肯尼亚并不适合女人生存...
Kenya is a hard country for women...
所以有骑士精神的存在
so there is a chivalry here, of a sort.
你是个有权力的人 而我实在是走投无路
You are a powerful man, and I have no one else to turn to.
我们私下再谈
Let's discuss this in the proper way.
你一定觉得尴尬 我失去了一切
You mustn't be embarrassed. I've lost everything.
- 求你是唯一的办法  - 等一下
- It costs me very little to beg you.  - Wait.
拜托 让她说完
Give her a moment, please.
这块土地本来是他们的
This land was theirs, you see.
被我们拿走了 害他们现在无处可去
We took it, and now they have nowhere else to go.
我会调查清楚 我们会尽力解决
I'll look into it. We'll do the best we can.
您可以向我保证吗?
May I have your word, sir?
我向你保证
You have mine.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我希望你会喜欢这里
I hope you will be happy here.
至少我是
I was.
可惜我没机会认识你
I'm sorry I won't know you.
我到了边界才听到消息
I didn't hear it until I got to the border.
看来我为了引起你的注意力 几乎是不择手段
It seems I'll do almost anything to get your attention.
我本来要你打包的
I've nearly got you packed.
我娘家都快被我拖垮了
And my poor family, I've got them near bankrupt.
我现在又要开口向他们要钱
Now I have to ask them for more money.
- 让我帮你  - 你是要留我?
- Let me help you.  - You would keep me, then?
不 我不想麻烦你
No. I want to be worth something now.
你有什么打算?
What will you do?
清仓拍卖以后 我就离开
After my rummage sale, leave.
星期五先到蒙巴萨...
Friday for Mombasa, and then...
然后搭船回丹麦
the boat to Denmark.
谢谢你 丹尼斯
Thank you, Denys.
叫他们一定要在下雨前 准备好离开
You must have them ready to leave before the rains.
那块地很大 够大家住
It is good land, enough for all.
他们不可以打架 更不可以惹麻烦
But they must not fight about it or be any trouble to the authorities.
你明白吗? 不然那块地就没了
Do you understand? Or they will lose it.
你要让他们明白 我不会在那边...
You must make them understand that I will not be here...
帮他们说话
to speak for them.
这块地远吗?
This land is far?
不是太远
Not too far.
以后要怎么办 你和我以后?
How can it be now with me and yourself?
你会有一点钱 我想够你生活
You will have some money. Enough, I think.
我不是在说钱
I do not speak of money.
还记得以前...
Do you remember how it was...
旅行的事吗?
on safari?
到了下午 我会派你先去前面找营地...
In the afternoons I would send you ahead to look for a camp...
然后你会等我
and you would wait for me.
你可以看到火...
You can see the fire...
然后到营地来
and come to this place.
对
Yes.
就像以前那样
Well, it will be like that.
只是这次我会先出发等你
Only this time I will go ahead and wait for you.
远不远 你要去的地方?
It is far, where you are going?
远
Yes.
你火一定要生的很大...
You must make this fire very big...
我才可以找到你
so I can find you.
把那个拿到外面去
Take that out to the lawn.
你吃过了吗?
Have you had dinner?
吃过了
Yes.
你的东西... 我帮你打包了
Your things... I packed your things.
我想我可以送到俱乐部给你
I thought I would send them on to the club.
没关系吧?
Is that all right?
这实在不是个好主意
This wasn't a very good idea.
我们要是早点这样就好了
I think we should have had it this way all the time.
我不知道
I don't know.
我开始喜欢你的东西了
I was beginning to like your things.
反而是我开始不喜欢
And I was beginning to like living without them.
你知道 都被你破坏了
You've ruined it for me, you know.
破坏了什么?
Ruined what?
孤独的自由
Being alone.
我有吗?
Have I?
我想陪你去蒙巴萨
I'd like to come with you to Mombasa.
我可以送你去吗?
Can I fly you there?
你不是要出门吗?
Aren't you going away again?
我明天要去察沃办些事情 星期五就回来
I have some things to do tomorrow at Tsavo, but I'll be back on Friday.
这样可以吗?
Will that be all right?
当然可以
Of course.
我最近学会一个新方法
I've got this little thing that I've learned to do lately.
生活非常不如意...
When it gets so bad...
我觉得撑不下去的时候...
and I think I can't go on...
我让自己更难过
I try to make it worse.
我开始回想我们的野外露营...
I make myself think about our camp on the river...
还有巴克利...
and Berkeley...
还有你第一次带我飞行
and the first time that you took me flying.
那些美好的回忆
How good it all was.
要是我实在撑不下去了...
And when I'm certain that I can't stand it...
我会再回想一件事
I go one moment more.
然后我就有勇气继续下去
And then I know I can bear anything.
想不想帮我?
Would you like to help me?
想
Yes.
那就和我跳舞
Come dance with me then.
你知道吗 你是对的
You were right, you know.
农场从来就不属于我
The farm never did belong to me.
也许我是错的
I may have been wrong.
我在非洲有座农场
I had a farm in Africa.
- 星期五  - 好
- Friday.  - Yes.
要不要喝杯饮料?
Would you like a drink?
好
Please.
丹尼斯死了
Denys has been killed.
他在察沃坠机
His plane crashed at Tsavo.
发生了一场大火
There was a fire.
我带你进城好吗 恬妮?
Can I take you into town, Tanne?
为什么他们派你来?
Why did they send you?
我觉得我该来
I thought I should.
天哪 你真勇敢
My God, you are brave.
"白日你不受太阳责打 夜晚你不受月亮苛责
"The sun shall not smite thee by day, nor the moon at night.
天主将保佑你远离邪恶
The Lord shall preserve thee from all evil.
他将保佑你的灵魂
He shall preserve thy soul.
天主将保佑你出入平安
The Lord shall preserve thy going out and thy coming in.
从此刻起 直到永远"
From this time forth and even forevermore."
阿门
Amen.
"那次你为镇上赢得比赛...
"The time you won your town the race...
我们为你欢呼过街市
we chaired you through the marketplace.
大人小孩为你喝采...
Man and boy stood cheering by...
我们抬着你回家
as home we brought you, shoulder high.
机灵的少年立刻溜过...
Smart lad, to slip betimes away...
田野上的荣耀短暂
from fields where glory does not stay.
月桂虽然早开...
Early though the laurel grows...
却比玫瑰早谢
it withers quicker than a rose.
你不会自我陶醉...
Now you will not swell the rout...
磨光他们的敬意
of lads that wore their honours out.
声名远播的跑者...
Runners whom renown outran...
他的名声消逝...
and the name died...
在他之前
before the man.
围绕着头戴月桂的他...
And round that early laurelled head...
人群凝视着无力的死亡...
will flock to gaze the strengthless dead...
发现未枯萎的月桂梢...
and find unwithered on its curls...
一顶荣冠...
a garland...
比少女的花环更短暂"
briefer than a girl's."
求你收回费奇哈顿的灵魂...
Now take back the soul of Denys George Finch Hatton...
你曾和我们分享
whom You have shared with us.
他带给我们欢乐...
He brought us joy...
我们深爱着他
and we loved him well.
他不属于我们
He was not ours.
他也不属于我
He was not mine.
如果我知道一首属于非洲...
If I know a song of Africa...
属于长颈鹿...
of the giraffe...
属于非洲新月的歌曲...
and the African new moon lying on her back...
属于田地的犁头...
of the ploughs in the fields...
和采咖啡工人的歌曲...
and the sweaty faces of the coffee pickers...
非洲是否知道属于我的歌?
does Africa know a song of me?
颤动的平原上空...
Will the air over the plain quiver...
是否仍有我的色彩?
with a colour that I have had on?
孩童是否会发明...
Or will the children invent a game...
以我为名的新游戏?
in which my name is?
满月抛下的阴影...
Or the full moon throw a shadow...
落在碎石车道上...
over the gravel of the drive...
是否像我的身影?
that was like me?
尼刚山的鹰是否会看顾我?
Or will the eagles of the Ngong Hills look out for me?
你不能跟我走
You cannot come where I am going.
你要去的地方有厨师吗?
There is no cooking where you are going?
相信我 你不会喜欢那里
You would not like it there. You must trust me about this.
你可以把信寄到丹麦的这个地址
Letters you can send on to this address in Denmark.
车子卖掉以后 麻烦把支票寄到猎人公司...
When you sell the car, if you would send the cheque to Hunter and Company...
其他无法处理的东西 也一块寄过去
and anything else you don't know what to do with.
是 夫人
Yes, ma'am.
男爵夫人 我们可不可以请你喝杯酒
Baroness, I've been sent to ask if we may stand you a drink.
- 谁是我们?  - 其实 是那些会员们
- Who is "we"?  - Well, the members, actually.
好
All right.
麻烦 威士忌
Whiskey, please.
麻烦 两杯威士忌
Two whiskys, please.
男爵夫人?
Baroness?
玫瑰唇少女 敏捷少年
Rose-lipped maidens, light-foot lads.
赞成 赞成
Hear, hear.
谢谢
Thank you.
这是我最珍贵的东西
This is very dear to me.
帮助我找到我的方向
It has helped me to find my way.
谢谢你 夫人
Thank you, msabu.
我想听到你叫我名字
I want to hear you say my name.
夫人 你叫凯伦
You are Karen, msabu.
今天收到的信中...
The mail has come today...
一位朋友告诉我
and a friend writes this to me:
"马萨伊族向尼刚区的官员报告...
"The Masai have reported to the district commissioner at Ngong...
好几次在日出 日落的时候...
that many times at sunrise and sunset...
在费奇哈顿的坟上看到狮子
they have seen lions on Finch Hatton's grave.
一公一母 常常走到那里...
A lion and a lioness have gone there...
站在或躺在坟上好长一段时间
and stood or lain on the grave for a long time.
你离开以后 坟墓周围的土地...
After you went away, the ground around the grave...
变成了一片倾斜的山坡地
was levelled out into a sort of terrace.
我猜这块平地对狮子来说 是非常理想的地点
I suppose that the level place makes a good site for the lions.
从那里可以俯视整片平原...
From there they have a view over the plain...
还有上面的牛群和猎物"
and the cattle and game on it."
丹尼斯会喜欢这样
Denys will like that.
我一定要记得告诉他
I must remember to tell him.
凯伦毕斯于1934年 出版第一本小说
笔名为艾萨丹森
她终生未再回过非洲